Inventory of Central Pacific Railroad Documents Collection MS 79 MS 79 MS 79
Test
- Series 3: Land Department Records, 1870-1949; 12 Volumes
  Restictions in place. Contact Library Staff for details.
  ¶ This series consists of twelve volumes of records and documents pertaining to the Land Department of the Central Pacific Railroad. The bulk of the series are the eight property map books ultilized by Central Pacific and Southern Pacific from 1910 to 1949. The books contain land grant information for properties in California, Nevada, and Utah which were owned by the railraods. Legal descriptions of the properties are given on each page of maps, with each section of land depicted divided into sixteenths. The volumes cover both Central Pacific and Southern Pacific Railroads, with four volumes for each. ¶
  ¶ The next largest group are the three volumes of day books used by Central Pacific to record the sale of lands in California from 1870 to 1883. They are arranged chronologically, and include entries for land purchase contracts, cancellations and deeds. Each entry notes the date of the transaction, contract numbers, the person(s) to whom the property was sold, terms of the sale, location of the property and amount received. Also included are right of way, mineral, or other reservations. ¶
  ¶ Finally, there is a single volume containing hand drawn station plans from circa. 1880. The plans were used by Central Pacific to build stations for their Salt Lake, Humboldt, and Truckee divisions in California, Nevada, and Utah. ¶
  Central Pacific Railway Company; Railroads--California--History
- Series 4: Personnel Records, 1864-1885; 7 Linear Feet 7 Boxes.
  ¶ This series consists of construction payroll sheets for the building of the Central Pacific Railroad. The payrolls are handwritten on printed forms and were issued by the railroad for "C[harles] Crocker, Contractor." The payrolls list the construction division for which the individual worked, rates of pay, and total pay received. The collection includes some payroll sheets for Chinese labor gangs, as well as payroll information for James Strobridge and other construction officials. ¶
  ¶ The payrolls are numbered consecutively for the period 1864-1865. A new consecutive numbering system seems to have been instituted in 1866, starting again with the number one. The payrolls are arranged by year and then by number. The CSRM Library does not have a complete set; there are missing numbers within each year. An inventory to the payroll vouchers, prepared when they were in the possession of Southern Pacific, has been placed in each box. While the inventory is not complete, it does identify specific Camps, Camp officials, as well as the vouchers which record Chinese labor. Refer to other MS 79 series for additional personnel information. View a sample payroll (No. 102 dated March 1865) online at: www.sachistoryonline.org.¶
  ¶ There is also a single volume relating to unpaid wages, 1882-1885. ¶
- Series 5: Equipment Records, 1868-1929; 3 Linear Feet 2 volumes and 2 boxes
  ¶ This series consists of two volumes and two boxes that contain an inventory of the equiptment and train cars used by the Central Pacific from the late ninteenth, to the early twentieth century. ¶
  ¶ The first volume provides the names of floating equipment or the numbers (old and new) of locomotives or cars, class of equipment, dimensions, weight, date in service and remarks, including disposition of the equipment. The cars listed in this volume are mainly an assortment of passenger cars (observation, sleeper, coach, etc), as well as shop and work cars used for construction and snow clearing projects. ¶
  ¶ The scecond volume contains similar information, but deals more with the weight capacity of box and freight cars. The volume also specifically lists fruit cars, cotton hoppers, and flat freight cars. Like the other volume, this one is dated between 1899 and 1929. ¶
  ¶ The two boxes contain mimeographed forms (Form 116: [form number was from original box; the forms have no numbers] with ink entries. In tabular form the following information may have been entered: owner, class, car number, date placed in service, capacity, original cost (actual / estimated), depreciation (percentage per year / amount per month), date vacated. One box has details the various car types used by specific branches of the Central Pacific Railroad. The two boxes are divided alphabetically, and cover the period between 1868 and 1808. ¶
  - Record Equipment Books
  - Rolling Stock
- Series 6: Miscellaneous Documents, Forms, and Correspondence, 1869-1903; 2 Linear Feet 2 Boxes
  ¶ Included in this collection are miscellaneous forms issued by the Central Pacific Railroad. By studying the types of information recorded, it is possible to learn details about the operation of the railroad and its personnel. This sampling represents but a minuscule portion of those issued or received by the Central Pacific. The forms have been arranged into two sub-series (blank and completed) and then by number or issuing department. The contents of these various documents range from waybill recipts and machinery department reports, to land department forms and livestock freight recipts. The forms range in date from 1869 to 1903 ¶
  Railroads--California--History; Central Pacific Railroad Company
- Series 7: Tariffs, 1875-1882; 5 Linear Feet 5 Boxes
  ¶ This series includes sample freight and passenger tariffs for the Central Pacific Railroad. There are also some joint tariffs, with the Union Pacific Railroad. Freight tariffs may list commodities, rates based on distance, and various shipping regulations. Tariffs come in various formats and are difficult to interpret unless one has all the appropriate issues and tables. Unfortunately, when a new tariff was issued, the previous edition was usually discarded, thus making it difficult for contemporary collectors to compile complete sets. ¶
- Series 8: Office of the Secretary, 1899-1917; 15 Volumes
  ¶ This series contains 15 volumes of bond ledger, recipt, and transfer books from the Central Pacific Railroad Company's Office of the Secretary between 1899 and 1917. The volumes are divided into three section. The first is three volumes mainly focusing on registered mortgage and gold rates from 1900 to 1914. The second are recipt books that cover a similar topic of gold and mortgage from 1900 to 1917. The final section deals with bond transfer books from 1905 to 1917. ¶
  - Bond Ledgers
  - Bond Receipt Books
  - Bond Transfers